so you've got in the hang of shooting
vertical videos for Instagram reels and
Tik Tok but you want to upgrade from
editing all of that on your phone to
your computer the absolute best way to
do that is with Final Cut Pro there are
a lot of great video editing tools out
there but Final Cut is the best way to
organize all your Clips put the good
parts in sequence and have something
ready to post as fast as possible and
the nice thing is it scales so we do
this as a business we not only create
our own social media but we create
hundreds of videos for clients every
year so today we're going to start from
the beginning creating a library and
scaling that up to be able to make as
many videos as you need let's get
started the first step is going to start
on our iPhone cuz that's where all of
our footage is this is a bunch of clips
that we shot at the rodeo recently and
you could just transfer everything all
at once select all of it I think today
it's going to be worthwhile to just
select my favorites and send those so
I'm not clogging out my computer quite
as much so then I can just look at all
my recent favorites select them all and
airdrop them to my computer now as these
transfer one note I'll make is that I
shot a lot of this in slow motion make
sure that you've edited that slow motion
the way that you want before you
transfer because you can't change it
afterwards so do it on the phone some
really quick steps in the finder before
we jump into Final Cut Pro I'm going to
create a folder called Rodeo highlights
and if I move through this stuff too
fast I have videos about the basics of
Final Cut Pro and if this video looks
familiar we're going to create a media
folder but that was a few years ago a
few iPhones ago I want to make sure
we're up to date so in that media folder
I'm also going to to create a folder
called video and audio and whatever else
might happen to be in the project you're
creating maybe you have images you don't
have to create more folders than you're
going to use and now we're going to grab
all of those airdropped videos drag them
into the video folder and we're on our
way now into Final Cut Pro we're going
to go to file new library and yes I
create a new library for every video
project that I'm going to create the
only exception is if a bunch of videos
share the same video clips then I could
use one library for multiple videos I'm
going to also call this Rodeo highlights
and to save some time I'm going to
select that text and copy it cuz I'm
going to use it once more and save now
if we go back to the finder we're going
to see that is what a library looks like
one thing I want you to keep an eye on
is the size of that Library I'm going to
try to show you how to keep it small
very common issue in Final Cut Pro is
the library balloons and becomes
enormous and it does not have to so I'll
show you all the settings in each know
just if that starts getting big double
check settings so now in Final Cut Pro
over here on the left this is your
library make sure it's selected I want
you to look at one thing before we get
in there on the right it says Rodeo
highlights standard gamma SDR did you
record your video in SDR or HDR because
the default on iPhone is HDR I recommend
everybody switch it to SDR if you don't
know you're going to have to look into
this but just make sure that it matches
the way that you shot everything I do is
in SDR great now we're going to import
our videos and there's a a big button
for it here which we could click or we
could go to file import or I'm going to
try to remind you guys of what some of
the most important shortcuts are and
Final Cut we're going to say command I
for import and the slow way to do this
is I could try to navigate to that same
folder but I'm going to do a little
shortcut go back to the finder and just
drag the media folder and now it's
showing me all of that content so I want
to import all of these videos there they
are I'm just going to click select them
all I'm pretty much ready let's just
take a look at these settings on the
right here most of the defaults are okay
we don't want to add a bunch of these
analysis features this will slow down
your import and you're probably not
going to end up using them anyway we're
going to look over here at files and
check out copy to library so what final
cat wants to do is put all of the video
clips and audio and all that inside of
the library so that's when it would
start to get big we're trying to avoid
that so we're going to manage it
ourselves and say leave files in place
rest of these defaults are fine import
selected and let's double check did the
Library get big it's only 4 megabytes
perfect that's just like metadata all
the library should be storing is
information about the edit but not the
actual files there's one more thing we
can do to prevent that bloat in Final
Cut we're going to go to settings and if
you click import you can change this
default for everything so I always have
that set to leave files in place and
then everything that you import will be
treated that way the one other change if
you have an M1 or newer Mac I strongly
recommend turning off background render
this was really useful with older Macs
that were tooo slow to playback footage
we just don't need this feature anymore
and it'll create a ton of huge cache
files you don't need and the last thing
just personal preference go to General
and switch color correction to color
wheels that's the industry standard I
think color boards are kind of weird but
that's up to you great okay we're ready
we've got all of our footage imported
into our browser this is our browser
here on the left they are inside of an
event you only really need one event for
most things I don't spend much time
worrying about events but as we move our
Mouse so long we can skim through and
see the highlights of our footage and
you can see I've kind of resized things
to optimize for this vertical view like
the default might be something like this
doesn't make any sense we're editing
vertical so let's kind of move it over
like that make sure we got enough space
with our timeline here and speaking of
we don't have a timeline yet let's
create our very first one we could
either click new project or like I said
I like shortcuts command in will give
you the new project dialogue we're going
to say command paste because remember I
copied Rodeo highlights that's the title
I always just title it the same thing as
the fold
and we have a shortcut called vertical
that can get us started in some of the
presets there's not a lot of
customization required here the defaults
are kind of close but vertical has some
like glitches I I don't know why it does
this first of all it goes to 720 that's
less than HD you want at least 1080 by
1920 that's normal HD footage you can do
4K but um social media doesn't support
it so when you upload it it's down
sampled to 1080 and even if you're
shooting in 24p it's converted to 30p so
for social media I find 1080 30p that's
like the good setting there's kind of a
bug in Final Cut That it switches the
color space to rec 609 instead of 709
you don't need to understand this 709 is
the standard I don't even know if this
matters if you change it but Rec 709 is
correct so I always do switch it let's
hit okay and now we've got all of our
footage over here on the left and a
timeline below we're ready to start
editing so depending how you shot your
footage and what you're trying to create
there's a lot of ways to work with this
usually the fastest one at work
especially for like a highlight reel I
think this is really fun you just select
all and drag that footage down see you
can tell it's selected cuz it's yellow
it's going to come up again yellow is
selected we're going to drag it down
into the timeline now we've got what is
this 24 minute and 40 second video that
is that is way too long so quick
shortcut we can just rightclick any of
that footage while it's selected say
change duration notice there's a
shortcut for this you don't need to
memorize it but change duration and this
is where it's displaying the duration
we're just going to say 1 0 for 1 second
and now every clip is going to play back
for exactly 1 second there are times you
can just throw this together and it'll
make good footage instantly without any
effort but today we're going to have to
do a little work cuz you're going to
notice that uh some of these clips
there's there's better moments so uh
here here's a good example I'm going to
zoom in command plus and here's the 1
second like that's not that's not the
good part so if I just click on the clip
it is selected because it's yellow and I
can see handlebars on the left and right
if I click and drag I can open up
everything that's inside of that clip
see kind of all the stuff that's
contained inside and keep expanding and
eventually oh there's the good part
that's what I was looking for okay so
what I really wanted was at the end of
the clip but it just selected the
beginning so lesson one that's a a
common way to edit your Clips you can
zoom in and out grab the handlebars and
move them around like that you're going
to end up needing to do that a lot but I
can show you a way that we can still do
this quick time change thing to get a
very fast edit out of here so instead of
the editing in the timeline I'm going to
do a little pre-editing I just select it
all and I'm going to hit delete clear my
timeline let's start from scratch come
back to the browser and it's worth just
spending a few minutes doing some basic
sorting in here there's a lot of
management you can do with very little
effort here because I can scrub through
and I can instantly see even from these
thumbnails like this is the cool part I
didn't even need to watch all this junk
up here I could just go straight to this
move my handlebars in the browser and
now I've selected the cool fire shot
make it smaller and if I drag that now
I've got the good part in my timeline
that's pretty good but I like shortcuts
more than clicking so I'm just going to
hover my mouse to this first frame of
the fire and press I for in so it's an
in point I'm going to move my mouse just
hovering to the end of the fire I'm
going to press o for out setting an out
point now I can click and drag and bring
that down or there's better ways there's
a shortcut I press the E key and that
drops it down so now I'm just going to
quickly go through all of my footage set
in andout points and press e like I
really don't need to spend too much time
here but make sure I find the good stuff
and that's what's finding its way into
the final edit and if you want to get
extra organized okay so this moment is
great what i' do is say in and out he's
getting in while another horse is riding
away I've got in andout points I'm going
to press f for favorite and you can see
there's a little green line that's been
added over that segment later I could go
back and just say show me my favorites
and it's like remembered that moment
that's we want to go one step further
we're not going to do that today we're
just going to drop them all right into
the time line and there we go just a
couple minutes and I've got a pretty uh
sensical timeline kind of makes sense
here I'm going to select all again use
that same trick change duration back
down to 1 second and look at this we've
got something that is a lot more
watchable we got fire and cowboys and
things make a little more sense so I got
a duplicate there now if you made a
mistake like I just did where I don't
quite have the right moment like the
horse starts to go by but not not quite
there okay I'm going to go into my tools
and look for trim now that's not true
we're not going to go into the tools I'm
going to press t for trim that's what
I'll do I'm going to press T and I'm
just going to move my clip left and
right until these previews show me that
the horse enters and kind of leaves the
frame and that's the 1 second that I
want make sure something cool is
happening same with this I just kind of
missed the fire there let's trim it to
make sure fire is going through that
whole shot and if I want to move Clips
around like put this fire Clips together
I can just move it to the left that's
the magnetic timeline of followup Pro
very helpful with quick edits like this
just kind of create some sense of order
here that makes a little more sense
which none of this actually does these
are kind of Random clips but I have also
the audio playing in the background of
these which I don't want like it's um
it's not professionally recorded audio
it's not helping tell the story here if
you look at the bottom of each clip you
can see the audio is still playing back
and I could just turn it down right
there locally on the clip I could do
that for each one that takes too long so
instead command a select everything on
the timeline and up here in the
inspector click on your audio tool make
sure that your volume is turned all the
way down I'll just say minus 99 uh or
you can grab the slider and move it
around and now there is no audio coming
from my Clips cuz I'm going to put
something much better in now if you
watched my videos before you have heard
artlist playing music in the background
cuz that's my go-to source for music and
audio effects and art list is the
sponsor of today's video so I'm going to
search for cowboy cinematic and there
are so many good cinematic Clips here I
love this new feature highlights that'll
just skip to the good part of the song
so I kind of know what it's all
about perfect I'm going to download the
MP3 usually I use the MP3 instead of the
wave cuz I don't need to edit it later
like the smaller file size now I'll go
back to the finder and remember we
created an audio folder very helpful we
can just drag the music in there there
is our audio so the way I like to add
this to Final Cut is actually just drag
and drop like I keep my finder window
open and I just grab the whole audio
folder and I drag it over to my final
cut event part of the reason I do it it
this way is now it has a keyword on it
see this key it is keyworded as audio so
I can find all of my audio together
later same trick works for video I can
drag that over now everything is in a
video keyword too there's a lot of ways
to use these keywords the keywords are
more helpful than events like some
people try to use these events as
folders the keywords are the way to
organize things now to say organized I'm
going to right click and say assign
audio rules this is music it ises not
dialogue now it's the right color I'm
going to drag it underneath zoom out and
just like my video I'm going to set an
in point and an out point for the good
part of the song all right pretty good
just need to trim the ends so that it
all lines up now we'll come back to our
list for some sound effects I'm going to
look for flames
of let's try strong wind driven flame
add it to the audio folder drag it over
now to stay organized assign audio roll
we're going to make an effect and just
make sure that it starts at the same
time as a flame and we're good to
go so I'm betting you've heard of
artlist before you know they have great
music or you've used them yourself cuz
like they're amazing but what you may
not have tried is their new voiceover
tool art list wants to be the go-to
platform with all of the assets that any
Creator needs they're the first ones to
have professional quality AI voiceovers
from professional voice actors I don't
know if you're as sick as I am of the AI
voiceovers on Tik Tok these sound so
much better so let me show you how you
can use them first you're going to go
through and just listen to some of the
different samples they have here every
child deserves someone who believes in
them once upon a time simplifying your
life means focusing on what so let's
narrow it down I kind of wanted it to
sound like this guy is narrating it so
let's say we're looking for a male we
can do video categories I'm going to go
for trailers select the voice and then
type what you want them to say up top
hit generate and in just a few seconds
really quickly we have our first voice
over there's more to a cowboy than a hat
and Boots that's not bad let's try
adding it to our video I have to turn
down our music to hear it there's more
to what cowboys than a hat and Boots all
right that voice is great but it's too
soft for what we're looking for let's
use that same text but this time rural
there's more to a cowboy than a hat and
boots oh yes that is what I'm looking
for that's great it's a way of life okay
so there's a few things you always want
to do when you're editing a voiceover or
a roll in Final Cut Pro if you've
recorded it yourself you're going to
have to master it but it's already
pre-master from artless or sounds great
still we're going to do the same thing
so let's say you wanted to change the
volume we might go into effects over
here and really often I go to levels and
I grab my limiter drop it on there and
this lets me just turn up the gain turn
up the volume without actually clipping
but since this is already loud enough
let's just turn it down as an example
here and see how that's edited the whole
thing but I might want to chop this up
so what I can do is I'm going to right
click and go to new compound clip or
shortcut I use all the time option G
creates a compound clip doesn't matter
what you name it say okay and a compound
clip is kind of like a folder if I
double click it I'm like inside of a
folder that has that same audio so now I
click back and I I'm back in my normal
timeline I can go in and out of a
compound clip and I'm going to add some
Cuts so I'm going to use command B for
the blade tool to trim between his
sentences here and kind of just break it
up so he says these things spread
throughout the whole video there's more
to a cowboy than a hat and boots but
then later I remember I forgot to add EQ
it's okay if I just double click any
part of it I'm back inside that compound
clip I can go grab my EQ drag it on top
and now that effect is changing
everything within the whole video maybe
I'm going to kind of scoop it like that
make sure the EQ is before the limiter
and now when I go back to my timeline
it's applied to the voice over all
throughout the same goes for a-roll this
is so powerful and useful any long clip
should be in a compound clip so you can
make these changes there's more a cowboy
than a hat and Boots okay but I want
that first sentence to have a little
more personality so I'm going to go back
to Art list and I'm just going to
regenerate that first sentence I'm going
to look at my voice settings and I can
do things like emotional range and I'm
going to crank that to Super expressive
and same with style let's give it a
little bit of a style boost now I'm
going to generate it again so let's see
the difference her first one sounded
like this there's more to a cowboy than
a hat and boots and now we're at this
there's more to a cowboy than a hat and
Boots which I love like you can go
through different performances with the
same voice and of course it also
understands punctuation so if this was a
question there's more to a cowboy than a
hat and boots I mean it's pretty good
like I I don't know I don't know how
they do it but this is really
professional quality voiceover work like
I'm I'm amazed what this is able to do
so quickly without having to send a
bunch of emails back and forth and
iterate you can just do it yourself all
in one place and all of these voiceovers
are covered by the artless license so
how get access to it well if you've
already got an artless Max subscription
like I do you've already got it it's
right there you can start playing with
it right now if you have a standard
subscription it's an easy upgrade or
there is a dedicated voiceover plan if
that's the only tool that you need from
art list or if you've never used art
list before you can create a free
account and just start playing around
with it use the basics and just see what
it's like so there's a link in the
description below I'd love it if you
click that to go check it out so that
they know you came from this video and
thanks again to artlist for sponsoring
this video now if you are recording your
voice over final cat has an amazingly
helpful new feature that I use all the
time let's say you're you're responsible
enough to leave the sink running while
you talk there's more to a cowboy than a
hat and Boots now that's a terrible
voiceover I would never actually record
it with that much noise in the
background but there is a really
powerful feature when you have your
audio selected go up here to your audio
tools and turn on voice isolation let's
hear it again there's more to a cowboy
than a hat and boots there's more to a
cowboy than a hat and boots there's more
to a cowboy there's more to a cowboy
this separates the voice in the
background and does a pretty good job of
it not as good as professional software
when I'm doing it for real I use isotope
RX tools that do an incredible job but
this is very usable often I'll just turn
it to 30% to subtly remove like say a
bit of air conditioning in the
background this one I've got to show you
if you haven't found it already best new
feature in Final Cut Pro in a while I
love it okay so this clip it's already
slow motion of the horse running but but
it's too fast I want this horse to run
by forever I want to be much slower so
in the olden days you could click on the
clip and then go over to here or you
know I prefer command R to bring up your
speed tools and then over top you've got
this little speed control and I could
just say slow 25% that's going to slow
it down quite a bit let's watch what
happens ooh that does not look good it's
stutters a lot for a while we've also
had better Optical flow this does some
frame blending so you can see it is
smoother but it looks weird like you
know this has been edited now check this
out we're going to go to smooth slow
motion this is using AI to do a lot more
work
25% and check this out it just it's slow
motion it's amazing it really fills in
those gaps and what's crazy is now I
could turn this all the way down to like
10% I would have never done this in the
past and now it's usable at 10% even if
you didn't shoot in 60 frames or 120
frames per second you can slow anything
down now I love this feature and the
fact that it actually works blows me
away but what really kills me is the way
Final Cut does color management it's
still not good I did a whole video about
editing log footage and Final Cut but
this is what they gave us instead so
here's a new tool so let's pick a clip
and up here in the top right we're going
to go to our color tools right now
there's no Corrections on it we're going
to add a color adjustment layer this is
relatively new and this is a machine
learning AI tool called enhance light
and color let's click it I just find it
to be pretty unpredictable like it's
using machine learning to average out
colors and sometimes it does a good job
but I find overall what it's doing like
let's try it again here
it wants to squash the highlights a bit
bring up the shadows and also it seems
to cool off the shadows in virtually
everyone like these it finds all these
images too warm like this should be a
good candidate color is pretty bad and
when I enhance it it it just doesn't do
what I would want it to do it just like
made the background kind of blue and uh
I don't know just made it all cooler and
more contrasty I just find it a bit
unpredictable and it seems like when the
feature came out everybody loved it on
first inspection but now that I've tried
it a few times I just I haven't found it
useful but what would be useful is color
management D Vinci resolve does it Final
Cut get on it I want color management
throughout the whole program that makes
sense but let's give him a little Credit
One new feature they did add that helps
is now I can rename those color
adjustment layers and say I don't know
this is like auto adjust you can name
each layer so that it's organized that
wasn't there before so it's a welcome
addition now since we're doing this on a
computer instead of a phone you can
really refine certain effects with more
detail than you could otherwise so I
just want to show you one cool trick you
do need an external plugin for this but
it's pretty awesome so if I grabb this
clip and I copy it and I paste it and
put it on top I'm going to open up my
effects and I've installed Roto AI which
is this really cool tool from motion V
effect drag it on top and let's actually
make this one clip a little bit longer
and again these are two of the same clip
on top of each other they're doing the
exact same thing I'm going to click on
the top one go into my roto Ai and just
kind of paint over myself quickly here I
don't have to do a very good
job then I'm going to hit tracker and
track forward and track backward all the
frames are tracked you can see AI has
cut me out for all of those instead of
merged I'm going to say masked video and
I'm going to add a title in here I know
it doesn't really fit but I'll grab this
one from nkb HD put it under this clip
of me walking and check this out put in
my own text make it bigger make it way
bigger and check that out isn't that
awesome like this used to be so hard
you'd have to like manually cut it out
and now you can just throw it together
in a few minutes and I've got to be
harsh about Final Cut Pro here because
this is one of the downsides of it when
you compare it especially to something
like resolve
tools like this are built into resolve
for free whereas you have to pay for a
lot of the plugins that I use all the
time in Final Cut Pro that's not ideal
like I I wish more of this was built in
I hope they keep adding and Final Cuts
not updating as fast as resolve but
resolve is way more complicated so is
Premiere Final Cut is so much faster to
edit in so that's why I keep using it
and now let's say we want to do some
color grading again this is Final Cut
color grading much simpler and quicker
than in resolve I'm going to go into my
titles and grab an adjustment layer if
you don't have an adjustment layer for
Final Cut Pro yet you kind of need it it
should be built in but at least this
one's free so all of the links will be
in the description for everything I'm
using in this video if you need that
Roto AI or adjustment layers or anything
um you can definitely find it down below
but let's throw an adjustment layer on
top of everything trigger right to the
end and now we're going to go into
effects go into color and drag a custom
L onto the adjustment layer now you're
going to have to grab a l from the
internet I have tutorials about this but
there are a million of them out there
I'll use one of my stalman lets and
check this out this is a lot more
cinematic I'll just kind of flip it on
and off as we're watching here you can
kind of turn the opacity up and down
depending how dramatic you want it to be
and this is just a great way to sort of
color the whole timeline all at once
sometimes you still need to go in and
like this clip is now a little too like
red and saturated so I might turn down
the saturation make it a little darker
you know you still might need to go
through and color correct each
individual clip but it's nice being able
to throw an overall look on top of
everything so that it's just kind of
ready to go and it's got a look to it
right away common question I get is how
to do captions in Final Cut Pro there is
a plugin called caption generator for
Final Cut it's in the App Store it does
its job well but it's very clunky to use
I actually usually end up just adding
captions inside of the social media app
instead of in Final Cut but we still
need to export this to make sure we have
the highest quality upload in the ends
so we're going to go to file and share
and Export or what I'm going to do is
I'm going to press command e which is
our export shortcut the info tab you
don't have to worry about this you can
change that later settings that's what
we're concerned about we're going to
make sure this is correct so there are
two common settings I use either in
audio and video you want to make sure
that well you're not exporting in Pras
that's too big for social media makes no
sense there's an h264 setting here that
is kind of the the largest quick preset
that you can do out of Final Cut Pro
that's the setting that I use most of
the time if you want to be a little bit
smaller but still great I also use the
Apple devices um multi-pass better
setting which also looks good A little
bit smaller little bit faster upload but
I prefer just my archive to be a little
larger so I'm going to let it be that
h264 you're just going to find whatever
your export folder is hit save and there
you go uh if you want to see the
progress it's up here in the top left
and before you upload one more step to
double check in Instagram and Tik Tok
and threads I noticed I had this turned
off the other day turn on highest
quality uploads they all have them in
different places in the settings so
search for where to turn it on but you
might have it turned off and you went to
all this effort of making it look
amazing and you upload it in standard de
instead of HD or who knows what and it
doesn't look as good as you want so
that's the last tip of this video I hope
this was helpful there was a lot to go
over so if you have any other questions
I've got a whole playlist all about
editing and Final Cut Pro and it's
definitely going to answer any of your
questions or just throw the questions in
the comments below and I'll get back to
you thanks for watching guys I'll see
you in the next
video there's more to a cowboy than a
hat and boots it's a way of life
it's about grit and
dedication and Rodeo is the chance for
every cowboy to share their passion with
the world
[Music]